Preliminary Inventory to the Sergei Petrovich Mel'gunov Papers, 1918-1933
Hoover Institution Archives
Sergei Petrovich Mel'gunov Papers,
1918-1933
38003
Mel'gunov, Sergei P., 1879-1956
17 manuscript boxes (7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Clippings, writings, correspondence and reports, relating to the Russian Revolution and Civil War, and the operations of the Soviet secret police. Also available on microfilm.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Agabekov, Georgii Sergeevich.; Dzerzhinskii, Feliks Edmundovich, 1877-1926.; Russian S.F.S.R. Chrezvychainaia komissiia po bor'be s kontr'revoliutsiei sabotazhem.; Soviet Union. Ob"edinennoe gosudarstvennoe politicheskoe upravlenie.; Civil rights--Soviet Union.; Secret service--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
Container List
- Individual Accounts of Witnesses and Victims, 1918-1920 (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - "In the Bolshevik Hospital, Petrograd, 1918-1919," by V. G. Orzhekhovsky, 1925.
  - "Kronstadt events in June-July, 1919," by Iu. Zubelevich.
  - "Red and White Terror," by A. T. Kuznetsov, Member of the Constituent Assembly from the Ural Region.
  - "Rumors and legends" (On Bolshevik stay in Kiev)
  - Bulletin of the Central Committee of the Party of Left Socialist Revolutionaries, April 1919
  - "In Yaroslav prison, 1920," by K. Marov Bishop Mitrofan of the Don reports on his arrest, 1918
  - "Two days in the Simferopol Cheka." (Folder 2)
  - "Lubianka 14-10," by G. V.
  - "Torture on the Moscow Bench," handwritten copy in Latvian from Brihwa Seme, No. 71, March 31, 1921
  - Account by American citizen Kalamiano: "In Butyrka prison, 1920."
  - "Analysis of Bolshevik terror," by M. I.
  - "In Bolshevik torture-chamber," by S. Vl-v.
  - Letter on certain "Ozolin."
  - "Chrezvychaika."
  - Notes on Butyrka Prison. (Folder 3)
- Clippings (Folder 4)
  - Soviet and non-Soviet papers, 1918-1919.
  - Terroristic measures after the attempt on Soviet officials in Lenot'evskii Per., Moscow, 1919 (Folder 5)
  - Communist arguments re Cheka, 1918-1919 (Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1919 (Folder 7)
  - Terror and executions, 1920-1921. (Folder 8-9)
  - Trials and executions, 1921-1923 (Box 2., Folder 10)
  - Arrests, trials, executions, 1924 (Folder 11-12)
  - Arrests, trials, executions, 1925. (Folder 13)
  - Arrests, trials, executions, 1926 (Folder 14)
  - Arrests, trials, executions, 1926 (Box 3., Folder 15)
  - Arrests, trials, executions, 1927 (Folder 16-18)
  - Donbass trials, 1928 (Box 4., Folder 19-20)
  - Donbass trials, 1928 (Folder 21)
  - Volfman's trial, 1928
  - Political prisoners, executions, 1928
  - Opposition, arrests, trials, executions, espionage abroad, 1929. (Folder 22)
  - Cheka, 1918-1927 (Folder 23)
- Cheka (Folder 24)
  - "Codification of Red Terror," article by Al. Makletsov.
  - "Political trials in the USSR," compiled by Ia. S. G- ch.
  - Resolution of the 3rd Regional Congress of Representatives, Guliaipole... and others, April 10, 1919
  - "Reign of Terror in Russia," manuscript by S. Melgunov, May 15, 1925
  - "Red Terror in Russia," manuscript by S. Melgunov.
  - "Ado Bizk," manuscript
  - "Execution of English officer Sidney Reilly," manuscript
  - Report of the Inspection Committee about the Cheka's Places of Detention in Poltava, manuscript signed by Dr. Mashevskii
  - Letter from Fedorchuk to Petrovskii, May 23, 1919
  - Statement by a member of the Central Executive Committee and Secretary of the Kiev Executive Committee addressed to the Cheka, April 8, 1919
  - Political Red Cross statement to the Presidium, 1921
  - Minutes of a Cheka meeting, July 25, 1919
  - Recollections of N. P. and U. S. Savitskii and M. V. Chernosvidov on arrival of Bolsheviks to Chernigov, January 23, 1918
  - Report No. 374 of Information Section, Head-quarters, Commander-in-Chief of the Russian army: Situation in Turkestan, Feb. 9, 1921
  - Excerpt from "Sotsialisticheskii Vestnik," No. 8, May 20, 1921
  - Report No. 563 from General Miller to Ambassador in Arkhangel'sk, April 19, 1919
  - "Kalinin and the G.P.U.," No 22
  - Authorization of the Foreign Communists-Bolsheviks to search foreign consulates, signed by Fisher, May 26, 1919
  - Kharkov Prison file on Mrs. D. A. Baeva
  - Death sentence of Aleksandr Grigorevich Bulygin, Riazanskie Izv. No. 201, Sept. 7, 1919
  - Left Socialist Revolutionaries in Bolshevik prisons, Bulletin No. 4, April, 1919
  - Activity of V.Ch.K. train in Voronezh Voronezhskie Izvestiia, No. 179 (484), August 12, 1919
  - Appeal to fight the enemies of the revolution, Kievskie Izvestiia, No. 99, July 24, 1919
  - Letters to Melgunov
    - Anna Nikulina, Bosna, Vlasenica, March 5, 1924
    - Baroness D. Foelckersam, February 23, 1924
    - F. Rostovtsev
  - "In Chernigov," recollections of E. D. Kuskova
  - "In Crimea," typewritten reports
  - "In cities and villages," Bulletin of the Left Socialist Revolutionaries, No. 6, May 1919
  - "Ukrainian Cheka," typewritten report
  - "Kiev," investigation of the Rerberg Commission, manuscript
  - Events in Kiev and Ukraine, 1918-1927 (Folder 25)
  - Statistical data on executions, 1918-1927 (Folder 26)
- Clippings
  - Cheka members (Box 5., Folder 27)
  - Cheka, 1919-1930 (Folder 28)
  - Cheka anniversaries (five, ten, thirteen years). (Folder 29)
  - Cheka, 1919-1929 (Folder 30)
  - Felix Dzierzynski (Folder 31-32)
  - Articles on OGPU by G. Agabekov from Poslednie Novosti, 1930 (Box 6., Folder 33)
  - "Death Camps," by Kiselev in Rul', 1931 (Folder 34)
  - "Work and Ways of the GPU," in Vozrozhenie, 1926
  - Confessions of GPU agent Nikolai Bezpalov in Volia Rossii, 1924
  - Georges Agabekov (Folder 35)
  - Chekist Albert Pirro (Folder 36-37)
  - Recollections on imprisonment, 1918-1925 (Folder 38)
  - G.P.U., 1919-1927 (Box 7., Folder 39)
  - "One week at the mercy of the G.P.U.," by Pavel Dolgorukov, Rul', 1924 (Folder 40)
- G.P.U. (Folder 41)
  - "O.G.P.U.," manuscript fy a former Chekist
  - Opperput's testimony on secret agencies.
  - Relations between NKID-GPU-Comintern
  - List of secret agents known to Opperput
  - Organization of the G.P.U.
  - Methods of operation
  - "Reorganization of the G.P.U.," from Poslednie Novosti
- Clippings (Folder 42)
  - Amensty for political prisoners on the 5th anniversary of the revolution
  - Persecution and trials of Social-Democrats, 1920-22
- Articles
  - "Wandering," by Gr. Aronson
  - "Notes of a prison warden," Gr. Aronson
- Cheka (Folder 43)
  - "Rare document," with commentary by A. Kuprin from Obshchee delo, November 7, 1921
  - Clippings on annulment of capital punishment, 1920
  - Clippings on local governments against Red Terror, 1918
  - Directives to local Cheka, December 1, 1918
  - Circular No. 2534 to all railroad and water transport Cheka commissions, June 11, 1919
  - "Five Years in Soviet Prisons," by Said Kureishi from Poslednie Novosti, 1927 (Folder 44)
- Clippings (Folder 45)
  - Cheka, 1920-1924
  - Recollections on imprisonment, 1921-1929 (Folder 46)
  - Insurrection, prisons, executions, 1925 (Box 8., Folder 47)
- Public Protest Against Terror
  - Letter from Roger Baldwin (Director, American Liberties Union) to Berkman. Translation from English to Russian, September 8, 1924
  - Questionnaire for former political prisoners
  - Mémorandum présenté par la délégation du Parti socialiste révolutionnaire à l'étranger au Congrès des trois unions internationales des partis socialistes et communistes, April 2, 1922
  - Appel au proletariat mondial, August 2, 1922, with Russian translation
  - Two bulletins of the Joint Committee for the Defense of Revolutionists Imprisoned in Russia, Berlin, 1925, 1926
  - Chronicle of persecution in Soviet Russia. Non-periodical bulletin, Berlin, 1924, Nos. 1, 2
  - Chronik de Verfolgungen in Sowjetrussland, Berlin, 1924
  - Clippings from various newspapers, 1921-1924
- Clippings (Box 9., Folder 49)
  - "Without Freedom," by A. Argunov from Na Chuzhoi Storone
  - "Four days in Lubianka," by I. Zakharin from Na Chuzhoi Storone
  - "Lubianka," by Nikolai Bezpalo from Volia Rossii
  - "Zalozhnik," by N. V. L'vov
  - Solovki, 1924-1930 (Folder 50)
  - "Dreadful Years," by Said Kureisha in Rul', " Taganka, Solovki, Butyrka," by Said Kureisha in Slovo, December 1926 (Folder 51)
  - "Peterburg - Solovki, Parizh," by S. Snezhevskii from Dni, 1927 (Folder 52)
  - "Solovki - Island of Torture and Death," by Mal'sagov in Segodnia, 1925
  - Bolshevik secret service and espionage, 1921-1930. (Folder 53)
- Maurice Conradi's Trial (Box 10., Folder 54)
  - Various documents, 1923
  - Clippings (Folder 55-60)
- Vorovskii's Assassination (Folder 61)
  - Clippings from Soviet Press
- Investigation of Bolshevik Atrocities (Box 11., Folder 62)
  - Establishment of a special commission
  - Rules and regulations of the special commision
  - Programme concerning activities of the special commission
  - List of photographs (photos not included)
  - List of findings
  - Testimonies of witnesses
  - Articles from Na Chuzhoi Storone
  - Reports of special commission (Folder 63)
- Clippings (Folder 64)
  - Foreigners on Soviet terror, 1920-1928
  - "In the Clutches of the Cheka," from Vozrozhdenie, August-September 1928 (Folder 65)
  - "Testimony of witnesses," Nikolaevsk na Amure, 1920 (Folder 66)
  - "Soviet Exile," by D. Viatkin, Volia Rosii
  - Red Terror, 1920-1930 (Folder 67)
  - On A. Pirro, P. Stuchka, Dzerzhinskii, Gen. N. V. Ruzskii, Prince Pavel Aleksandrovich, V. P. Mukhin (Folder 68)
  - V. Brunovski case (Folder 69)
  - Insurrections in Kronstadt, Karelia, Amur Events in Crimea, Caucasus, Ukraine
  - Izvestia, June 24, June 26, August 29, 1919 (Folder 70)
  - "Notes of a former Soviet Lawyer," by E. Nagel' in Poslednie Novosti, 1933 (Box 12., Folder 71)
  - "Peterburg-Solovki-Parizh," by V. Svezhevskii in Dni, 1928
  - "Reminiscences of Princess S. A. Volkonskii," by N. Chebyshev, reviewing Gore Pobezhdenym, 1933
  - "His Serene Highness Appearing Before the Chairman of the Cheka," by R. Vel'skii reviewing Gore Pobezhdenym, 1933
  - "Escape of Princess Palei," by A. Lidin from Slovo, 1920
  - "Interrogation," short story by A. Kuprin from Vozrozhdenie, 1930
  - Individual accounts of witnesses and victims, 1929-1935 (Folder 72)
- Illustrated Bolshevism, published by Dvuglavyi Orel, 1922 "Appeal to the American People," Paris, November 7, 1930 (Folder 73)
- Chronicle of Red terror from Bor'ba za Rossiiu (Folder 74)
- Clippings (Folder 75)
  - Chekists (Dzerzhinskii, Menzhinskii, others)
  - Accounts of Red terror by foreigners, 1928-1933 (Folder 75-78)
  - Accounts of former Chekists, 1926-1932 (Folder 79)
- Clippings on arrests, trials, executions, 1918-1930 (Box 13.)
- Report by Iu. Kluchnikov to the Russian Political Conference in Paris when he was no longer in charge of the Omsk Foreign Ministry, June 2, 1919. Deals with the Ufa Directorate, Kolchak cou d'etat, Kolchak government, etc.
- Telegrams between anti-Bolshevik political leaders concerning policy on former Russian borderlands, January-December 1919
- Political conference in Paris, unsigned reports and letters on the anti-Bolshevik Russian policies with regard to national minorities (Baltic States and Belorussia).
- Savinkov and others on Polish problem, 1920
- Attitude of the Allies. Interview in Kiev
- Manuscript on the Ukranian question by the Delegation of the Political Conference, Paris, September 1, 1921
- Letter from Gen. Boldyrev to Chaikovsky on the situation in Siberia, March 26, 1919
- Letter to S. S. Maslov to Chaikovsky, November 3, 1918
- Telegram to Russian representative in Copenhagen from the Provisional Russian Government formed on September 23, 1918, on organization and work of the new government, October 2, 1918
- Kolchak Government official telegrams on military and political problems in Siberia, December 1918 - December 1919
- Memorandum by S. I. Morozov on organization of revolt against Bolsheviks in Siberia on May-June 1918 and on organization of Siberian government September 12, 1918
- Memorandum to Admiral Kolchak from Allied and Associated Powers; Kolchak's reply, July 1, 1919
- "Kolchak's Crime," manuscript by Aleksandr Goibarg, Head of the Department of Justice of the Siberian Revolutionary Committee
- Declaration of the Provisional Government, 1918
- Report on circumstances connected with the deportation of five members of the Provisional Government to Solovki, September 5-6, 1918. Chaplin's coup d'etat.
- On the upheaval in Arkhangel'sk, 1918
- Official correspondence (mostly telegrams) of the Provisional Government. September 1918-October 1919
- Excerpts from minutes of the March 26, 1919 session of the Provisional Government
- Chaikovsky correspondence re northern region
- Correspondence between Gen. Miller and Sazonov, March-April 1920 re winding up the northern campaign and future plans following defeat
- Gaida's revolt in Vladivostok.
- Informatsionnyi listok, illegally published by the Union for the Regeneration of Russia, August 1918
- Nikolai V. Chaikovsky correspondence with Ekaterina K. Breshko-Breshkovskaia
- Nikolai V. Chaikovsky's correspondence
- Nikolai V. Chaikovsky's speeches
- Va. A. Bakhmetev, former ambassador to the U.S. (under Kerensky) on U.S. attitude toward anti-Bolshevik movement, October 21, 1919
- V. A. Bakhmetev on policies to be pursued in anti-Bolshevik movement, March 18, 1919
- "First Anniversary of the Kronstadt Garrison Mutiny," Krasnaiia Gorka, by M. N. Nekliudov, Summer 1919
- Translated excerpt from M. Merts' Sagies Latwija'., Riga 1925.
- Donskoi Krai, No. 12, May 5 (18), 1918. Organ of the Provisional Government of the Don. Contains article "The Germans in the Ukraine."
- Vestnik Vremmenogo Pravitelstva Severnoi Oblasti. Newspaper published in Arkhangelsk, December 17, 1918; January 1, 1919; September-October 1919 (incomplete)
- A. A. Neratov, telegrams, 1919 (Box 14.)
- Copy of the Resolution of the Extraordinary Kuban Regional Rada (Council), November 11, 1918
- Declaration of the Don Voisko Krug (Parliament), June 1, 1919 on future Russia as a democratic country
- Copy of Report on Cossak uprising in the Upper Don Region against Bolsheviks, spring 1919
- Minutes of the Supreme Krug (Parliament) of the Don, Kuban, and Terek regions, January 1920
- Declaration of the democratic groups in South Russia, January 29, 1920
- Statement in French re formation of a new democratic government in South Russia
- Provisional Land Law Project of the government in South Russia, February 24, 1920. Drafted by Pavel Ageev.
- Report of events in the last days of the Council of Ministers of the government in South Russia, April 6-9, 1920
- Letters to Nikolai Chaikovsky on the situation in South Russia, 1919-1921
- Appeals of the Russian delegation in Yassy to Allied powers, November 1918
- Memorandum (in French) presented to Allied governments by the National and Democratic Russian Bloc on aid to Russia by Allied powers and the United States
- Kerensky's activities and impressions abroad in connection with the Allies' attitude to the Russian anti-Bolshevik cause, 1918. Letters, telegrams, etc.
- Documents of the Russian Political Conference and of the political delegation representing Russian anti-Bolshevik governments before the Allies in Paris, 1918-1919.
- British attitude to the Russian anti-Bolshevik cause, 1919
- Chaikovsky's correspondence re French and British attitude to Russian anti-Bolshevik cause, 1919
- Chaikovsky's memorandum to Clemenceau on Russian anti-Bolshevik cause, 1918; and Chaikovsky to President of the Council of Great Britain.
- Extract from a letter to Mr. Paul Boyer, June 21, 1918 (in French)
- Speech by Menard-Dorian, May 6, 1919 (in French)
- Reports from prison, 1912
- Clippings
  - Mensheviks, 1930-1931
  - Uprising in Siberia, 1925-1931
  - Various trials, 1927
  - Trials of Kondrat'ev, Groman, others, 1930-1931
  - Execution of the "48," 1930
  - Reprisals against the Chekists, 1925-1932
  - Shakhtinskii trial, 1928
  - Trial of the "Industrial Party," 1927-1930
  - Events in Moscow, 1925-1931
  - Events in St. Petersburg, 1925-1927
  - Events in the Ukraine, 1925-1931
  - Events in RSFSR, 1925-1930
  - Events in the Caucasus, 1925-1933
  - Events in Turkestan and the Urals, 1925-1932
  - GPU abroad, 1921-1933 (Box 15.)
  - Russian Chekists in Romania, 1932
  - GPU methods, trials, executions, 1931
  - GPU, 1932
  - Trial of I. Shtern, 1932
  - Fugitives from the U.S.S.R., 1932
  - Prisons and exiles, 1932
  - Executions, 1932-1933
  - Red terror, 1934
  - Gen. A. P. Kutepov affair, 1930
  - Arrests, trials, executions, etc., 1926 (Box 16.)
  - Arrests, prisons, exiles, 1928-1929
  - Opposition to Cheka, 1928-1929
  - Executions, 1928-1930
  - Fugitives from the U.S.S.R., 1930
  - GPU, 1930
  - Protests in Western Europe, 1930
  - Exiles, 1930
  - Executions, 1931
  - Prisons, exiles, trials of saboteurs, 1931
  - Trials of saboteurs, 1932-1934
  - Arrests, exiles, trials of saboteures, 1933
  - Trial of British saboteurs, 1933 (Box 17.)
  - Trials and executions after Kirov's assassination, 1934
  - Executions, prisons, exiles after Kirov's assassination, 1935
  - Executions, prisons, exiles, 1936
  - Trials of Trotskyists-Zinovievists, 1936
  - Trials, executions, etc., 1937
  - Trial of the "17," 1936-1937